Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Additional Railroad Booklets 5894
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Additional Railroad Booklets
1926-1973
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen (BRT)
5894
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
These are the papers of Carl N. Smith, a brakeman and conductor on the New York Central Railroad, Grand Central Terminal Division. Mr. Smith was a member of the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen [BRT], and served as a legislative representative, vice-president, and president of the BRT Metropolitan Lodge, Local 598.
5727804
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, July 12, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, July 12, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen was founded in 1883 in Oneonta, N.Y. as a protective and insurance organization. By the time of its merger with three other railroad labor unions to form the United Transportation Union in 1969, it had the greatest membership of any of the operating railroad brotherhoods.
The Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen [BRT] was established to represent members' interests in obtaining a satisfactory contract with management. The first Canadian lodge was established in Moncton, New Brunswick in 1885, and the first Ladies' Auxiliary was organized in Fort Gratiot, Mich. in 1889. These records reflect the union's political and fraternal activities as well as its actions in the areas of collective bargaining, grievances, and railroad and labor legislation. As the largest of the unions which merged to form the United Transportation Union in 1969, the bulk of its then current files formed the basis for the files now held in the merged union's headquarters.
The rail service members of the BRT included conductors and their assistants, dining car stewards, ticket collectors, train baggagemen, brakemen, and train flagmen. The yard service members of the BRT included yardmasters, yard conductors, switchtenders, foremen, flagmen, brakemen, switchmen, car tenders, operators, hump riders, and car operators. In 1933, the BRT organized interstate bus operators, and included them under BRT contracts held with U.S. bus companies.
BRT officers were elected at the Grand Lodge Convention of the Brotherhood, held every 4 years. The principal officers included a president, an assistant to the president, a general secretary-treasurer, Canadian and national legislative representatives, a senior vice-president, BRT representative, and National Railroad Board of Adjustment representative. The BRT had four governing boards: the Board of Directors, Board of Trustees and Insurance, Board of Appeals, and Executive Board.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1926-1973
Bulk dates: 1954-1973
This collection consists of materials collected by Carl N. Smith, an employee of the New York Central Railroad [NYCRR], Grand Central Terminal Division and member of the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen [BRT]. He collected pamphlets from the BRT, including the BRT's constitution, agreements between the BRT and NYCRR, the By-Laws for Local 598, and general information on the union. He also collected rulebooks and timetables from the NYCRR's Grand Central Terminal Division. He also collected materials on first aid for railroad workers and on the Railroad Retirement System.
Of particular note is the correspondence file, which documents the various actions taken by rank and file members of the BRT in the 1950s, 1960s, and 1970s. Specific concerns that the rank and file members were concerned with include sanitation concerns at Grand central Station, the abandonment of lines, the repeal of the full crew consist in New York State and the subsequent loss of jobs, the perceived disinterest of the higher ranked union members for the concerns of the rank and file, and the state of the Railroad Retirement Fund. This collection also contains a pamphlet advocating for a union that served all railroad operating employees, and in correspondence Mr. Smith and his fellow rank and file members expressed similar desires.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5021: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Additional Records 5102: Emergency Board No. 129, Long Island Railroad and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Locals 517 and 1090, Records 5149: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Records 5149 MB: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Memorabilia 5149 P: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Photographs 5348: W.P. Kennedy as President of the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen against the Long Island Railroad Company Court Documents 5446: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Ledger 5612: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Moosic Tunnel Lodge no.93 Meeting Minutes 5623: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Legislative Board of New York Files 5631: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul and Pacific Railroad General Committee File 5647: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Joppa Lodge (Toledo, OH) Minute Books 6268 P: Joint Committee of Adjustment for the Rock Island System's Order of Railway Conductors and Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Photograph 6312 P: Judith Sullivan Kowalczyk Collection of Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Photographs 6312 PUBS: Judith Sullivan Kowalczyk Collection of Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Publications 6312m: Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Annual Report of the Legislative Board 6405 PUBS: William Sharp Collection of The Railroad Trainmen's Journal 6480 MB: Paul Berger Collection of Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Memorabilia
Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions; Railroads -- Employees -- Pensions -- United States; Railroads -- New York (State) -- New York; Grand Central Terminal; Smith, Carl N.; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen. Metropolitan (NYC) Lodge 598.; New York Central Railroad; United States. Railroad Retirement Board.
5727804
- Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen pamphlets, 1954-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: State and Federal Laws: Commission Rulings and Regulations on Buses, 1952; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    To Member of the Brotherhood of railroad Trainmen in the State of New York. C.H. Sullivan, New York State representative, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen
    Format: Pamphlet.
  - Item 2: Proposed Changes in By-Laws, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Metropolitan Lodge No. 598, 1954; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    (Typed copy of pamphlet)
  - Item 3: Your Labor Union: A brief sketch of its history, functions and accomplishments, 1959; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Published by the brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Cleveland, Ohio
  - Item 4: Manual of Information and Instructions (formerly negotiating manual), 1962; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Part I: Protective Department; Part II: Legislative Department.
  - Item 5: Constitution, 1954; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen and Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Insurance Department. Amended at the Thirtieth Convention held at Miami Beach, Florida
- Report of the Legislative Board, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, State of New York, 1963; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 2)
  by E.A. martin, legislative representative
- Agreements between New York Central Railroad Company and the BRT, 1926-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: Schedule of Rules and Rates of Pay: Conductors, Trainmen, and Yardmen, 1926; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    New York Central Railroad (Buffalo and East)
  - Item 2: Agreement Governing Rules of Pay of Assistant Conductors, Ticket Collectors, Baggagemen, and Brakemen, 1936; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Between the New York Central Railroad Company, Eastern District (except Boston and Albany Division) and New York District, and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen
  - Item 3: Agreement Governing Rules and Rates of Pay of Yardmen, 1953; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Between the New York Railroad Company (Buffalo and East) Including Troy, Union, and Catskill Mountain Branch, and the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen
  - Item 4: Agreement Governing Rules and Rates of Pay of Yardmen, 1955; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 3)
- New York Central Railroad, Rule Books, 1926-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- New York Central Railroad (New York District) G.C. Terminal Division, Hudson Division: Timetable No. 22, 1967; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 5)
  For employees only
- General railroad pamphlets, 1945-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: First Aid Instructions for Railroad Employees, 1951; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    As revised January 1951 by Medical and Surgical Section, Operating-Transportation Division; Association of American Railroads
  - Item 2: You and UROC: A brochure of information for the railroad crafts, 1952; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Published by the United Railroad Operating Crafts
  - Item 3: Questions and Answers on Proposed Amendments to the Railroad Retirement, Railroad Unemployment Insurance, and Carriers Taxing Acts, 1945; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Prepared by the Railway Labor Executives' Association
  - Item 4: The Railroad Retirement System: Its Coming Crisis, 1972; Pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Excerpts from the Report of the Commission on Railroad Retirement. U.S. Government Printing Office.
- Correspondence re BRT and concerns of rank and file members; BRT dues receipt for Carl N. Smith, 1958-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)